No.
Who eats your dinner?
Am I muted now?
Alright. We're live.
>> Sorry about that. My Comcast
and
leave me in the lurch.
And you're you're freezing up, George.
>> Just out of curiosity, does anybody know if George is attempting to call in by phone now? Or
I don't know. I was wondering that too.
>> Hey, Joe.
Would we have a plan b if if George
can't get back on? Meaning, could he go to the town hall and
log on something?
>> Probably. I don't know what. I mean, he could use my computer, I suppose.
Just
just
thinking out loud here.
Mhmm. I
don't see a work clerk on either.
>> Is Mindy here? No. She's not. She's on
the road today, so
I'm doing the recording. She'll do the minutes later.
>> Okay,
am I audible?
Yes, you are. Yes. Okay, good. So as I was saying, I just switched to a different device, and hopefully this one will be stable
for the duration of the meeting.
So as I was saying,
our
order of business is the
approval of minutes
for May 3. Do I have a motion to
approve?
Did you call the meeting to order, George? Yes, I did. I was probably in and out of
connection
when I did so.
You and Commissioner Hallisey are the only ones on the commission for the meeting, so that
pretty much truncated the
roll call and the seating of commissioners.
>> I'll move to
approve the minutes of May 3
as written.
And I'll second. Okay.
Any
corrections
or
additions to
the minutes?
I had none.
>> Okay.
Hearing none, then I will call for a vote by
roll call. Commissioner Hallisey?
Aye.
Commissioner Larson? Aye.
And I, Vice Chairman Elliott,
vote aye. So, the motion to approve the minutes carries three-zero-zero.
Next item on the agenda,
old business
IWWC
2036,
the 2600 Old Farms Road application.
We've received, of course, new information
requested by the commission at previous meetings.
And I wonder if
let's see now.
Agent Wagner, could you
speak to those changes, and then we'll hear from the
applicant or their agent
regarding the basic summary
of the new
information that's been received.
>> Okay. Yeah, we got
two
supplemental information
packages from engineer
Karl Achimovich.
And I think it was dated May 25.
So there's one that has
drainage analysis for the floodplain. There's another one that elaborates a little more on it. And then there's a
letter from engineer Brandon Handfield
with his recommendations to the commission
that also came in.
Those are all posted on the website.
>> Right.
Is Agent Hanfield on the call? I can't see all the participants
on this.
I'd like someone to walk us through
the at least a summary of the information
that's been received.
Hopefully, Brandon's on.
Maybe
engineer Bushnell could start us off.
>> Okay.
Fine with me.
Mr. Bushnell, if you would
Yep. Take it away.
>> So
basically, Carl analyzed
the the the upstream and downstream conditions for the twenty five and the hundred year storm. Now the subdivision regulations only require us to do
For twenty five year, but we went, you know,
a couple extra steps and went to one hundred year.
It's a twenty five year. I believe it showed no
increase in in,
water levels upstream.
At the hundred year, there was a slight increase of nine tenths of a foot,
right in the vicinity
of the, of the crossing there.
And
you know it 100.
A hundred year storm. Shows an outlet velocity of 4.8 feet per second, which is pretty pretty low velocity.
So
you know we believe that you know the upstream impact
as far as a flooding condition, nineten of a foot is pretty minimal. You know you're talking one hundred year storm and it's going to happen once every one hundred years theoretically,
and it's going to be, you know, contained right to the area near the crossing.
It's not going to affect any houses or anything important on the upstream properties.
You know, like as I said, the twenty five year, which is required by the subdivision regulations
is, you know, no increase in the in the elevation of the water level in the upstream
flow.
And then we believe, you know, 4.8 feet per second, that's at a hundred year storm.
You know, we're gonna put riprap in the in the, you know, at the outlet on the downstream
side of the crossing.
Probably getting some larger size riprap and concrete some of that in to make a real sturdy outlet splash pad to slow that velocity to 4.8 down even more and to spread it out wider.
You know,
upstream there's, you know, I'd call it a gentle slope channel that's, you know,
covered with with leaves and stick debris understory cover.
You know, Carl and I have been out there when we originally started this job. There was no flow and how we picked up on that there was an intermittent flow was there was some sticks and some
leaves move there from a, you know, probably from a larger storm.
Larger, you know, velocity flow that moved them just a little bit, and that's how we could pick up where the flow paths were out there.
So, you know, we would anticipate something like that in the largest storm would occur. I mean, there's going to be some natural.
You know disturbance of the area
anyways in a in a larger storm and what we don't expect anything more than really what's what happens now.
You know, on the downstream.
Condition, same thing. The slope there really starts to flatten out downstream or where the proposed crossing is, and the flow widens out significantly
once it hits the neighbor's yard downstream.
So then again, you know, between the the the
minimal slope of the channel, the the width of the channel, the wide width of the channel
and the outlet
protection, you know riprap, the protection pad that we're going to construct there. We don't anticipate any
any detrimental,
you know, effects downstream either from this this crossing installation.
You know, and we are, you know, we are designing it for the one hundred year storm. If we were just doing the twenty five years required,
you know, you would see larger, I believe, and Carl can correct me if I'm wrong. You'd see larger
velocities through these through this box culvert and through the pipe because
you'd have a lot more head pressure
on on them in a one hundred year storm. They wouldn't, you know, you wouldn't have the area. The pipe wouldn't be as big. The culvert wouldn't be as big to pass just a 25 storm, so you get more velocity at the outlet.
You know, by overdesign is still one hundred year, we're really going
above and beyond to try to mitigate, you know, the potential
for downstream effects
by decreasing the velocity.
>> Okay,
thank you for that. I'll ask if any of the commissioners have any questions
regarding the reports. I see that
Engineer
Smovic is on the call now, if that's Carl too.
Yes, that's right. Okay. Very good. So
I'll again turn it over if either the commissioners have any questions.
>> Yeah. It's Jim Hallency.
First of all, I just wanted to to thank, Brandon in absentia for turning
this around very quickly.
But I do have a question to the chair,
if I may, of Andrew Bushnell.
Go ahead.
>> Okay.
And I have to assume that,
Andrew, that you had an opportunity to to review
Brandon's
submittal,
and I just wanna
know that you feel comfortable,
Frank, providing the two certifications that are suggested.
>> Not really.
I mean, we can't certify to everything. I mean, there's other factors out there that could cause problems
in that channel that, know, somebody could do something upstream to obstruct it or open it up. The tree could fall down upstream and you could get sticks washing down or a big limb that would plug up
culvert. Know there. I mean there's things that could happen out there that we have no control over and that we don't situations that we don't create, know.
So I mean you can't certify 100% that nothing's going to happen out there and that's kind of
where we feel he's pushing us to you know.
>> Could I just say something here? Go ahead.
Just want to reiterate that you know for the twenty five year storm
there's no impact at all in terms of
any increases along the line because the culverts can handle that easily.
For the one hundred year storm, we have to remember
statistically,
this is a once in one hundred year occurrence,
one time.
And we're talking about a shallow increase of nine tenths of a foot in one section
upstream of where this driveway crossing is going to be located.
So it's not a large impact.
In terms of
impact, what Brandon has suggested here, impact to the side slopes
of the gully that's there.
It's very smooth along the bottom, has shallow slopes on the side, the approach velocity is very low.
And I can say that there's not going to be any substantial impact. And again,
we're looking at something occurring once in one hundred years. Under normal conditions,
like when Andrew and I went out there,
you had a hard time figuring out where the channel was even located because there's so little impact.
And then as far as on the downstream side,
what happens is when a culvert opens up, as Andrew has indicated,
you spread out to a wide section and it gets wider as it goes past
House Number 74, the last house, before it gets down into the floodplain area.
And it just gets very wide and the impact is low, the velocities are low.
And
again, you know, with the one hundred year analysis, looking at a really, really rare occurrence, one time, under normal conditions,
you're not going to even see an impact here.
Okay,
>> thank you. So, you know, if I could just add here,
the certification
is,
you know, I can say unequivocally,
we're not going to have any major impact.
But to anticipate
every potential situation, as Andrew has indicated,
debris could come down, something could clog things up.
People may be doing stuff in
the low area upstream of where the driveway is going be located.
There's a myriad of things that can happen, especially when you're looking over a span of years or decades.
So we
foresee every possible situation that could occur here.
But under normal conditions
and normal maintenance of this area,
we are not going to see anything detrimental,
particularly for
the storms
that we've analyzed for.
And again, the worst situation you're looking at
here is around House Number
68,
where I have cross section five shown on the plans.
There's a potential nine tenths of an increase
in
the water surface elevation due to the one hundred year storm,
not to the 25, there's none for the 25,
which is your requirement.
And even at that, if we look at the next sheet,
which indicates
the elevation of the house at cross section 5,
the house elevation or ground elevation behind the house is approximately three forty two,
and the highest water surface elevation
for the one hundred year
storm is 328.2.
So we're looking at an approximate
nine foot difference in elevation
from the back of the house, the low point of the back of the house to the water surface down in the low area.
Okay.
>> You know, I believe we realize that you
can't
foresee every possible
contingency,
and especially VAV what might happen upstream
in the future.
But,
I think we can take your assurance that as a result of the proposed
activity
per se,
there will be no impact
or negligible
impact
on either upstream or downstream conditions.
Okay.
Commissioner Hallisey,
does that satisfy
your
original
inquiry?
>> I'm compelled to just
raise the issue that the
definition of one hundred year flood
is not consistent with
what I understand a hundred year flood to be, but it's it's neither here nor there. I'm I'm comfortable with with the response.
>> Are we talking about the, you know, one hundred year rainfall event versus?
>> It's a 1% in any given year. I mean, that's a given definition
I
understand it,
as opposed to
You're correct. Yeah. Happening every 100 years. I'm sorry. It's just it's just something that I had I had to read. I'm sorry. Okay.
>> Okay. Well,
thanks for that point of correction.
Commissioner Larson, did you have any further questions regarding
the application
or the,
supplemental information?
>> I did have a couple. And the first one is
for you on,
would it be appropriate for us to put a condition of approval that the applicants would keep the culvert clear
to try and mitigate the
debris clogging?
>> If I might add something there, think I would agree with that.
And I think maintenance,
because
I look a lot of dams throughout the state,
and maintenance is
extremely important. So to me, that would be a pertinent condition to add to any approval.
>> And
from my perspective, yes, we can certainly
add that as a condition of approval.
My only
question then would be
how would we make sure
that that is
enforced,
or
that there's follow-up,
you know, past our institutional
memory,
and without
over tasking our agent
with the need for annual inspection.
>> Yeah, I'm not suggesting
that we do anything like that. We just make it clear to the applicant that we expect them to keep the debris out of the way so that it allows
good flow.
>> I agree. I mean, realistically,
there's drainage swales, etcetera,
on many
development projects.
If they're not maintained, they fail, and that's a given.
Everything requires maintenance. We
have a lot of long driveways in town,
a lot of swales,
and a lot
lot of of them do fail.
But nonetheless, I think it's a great condition.
>> I mean, think these culverts, the culverts, 36 and the box culvert will
be a three by eight or so by the time we fill in. Well,
36 is going to get filled in a little bit too, but they're they're going to be big openings, so you know it's not going clogged by the little common
kind of things that would clog a typical driveway culvert or swale. Know it'll take quite
larger piece of debris to to plug these so.
I think it'll be pretty obvious that it needs to be maintained when you get some kind of debris like that in front of it, plugging it up, you know, or starting to plug it up, you know.
But your everyday debris, I think, gonna is gonna wash right through there like it does now.
>> Well, and that
brings me to my
next question, I guess, is
I'm still confused on the size of the box culvert.
And we've been talking about the box culvert being a four by eight foot
box.
When I look at the drawings,
it refers to it as a
three by eight foot
four sided box.
I know last time we talked about it being four foot with
a foot of dirt in the bottom limiting it to three.
Right,
>> right. Think, yeah. Yep. But if I look at the
detailed drawing that actually shows the culvert,
it shows
the culvert
three feet high
with three quarters of a foot of dirt in the bottom.
So
>> Okay, yeah. It is what's on the plan.
It's what's on the plan there.
We're filling it in.
>> I understand we're filling it in. But on the plan, we're filling in a three foot opening
with three quarters of foot. So it's only two and a quarter foot opening.
And I'm just trying to
gain an understanding of what it is that we really expect to see when we go out and see the driveway done.
>> You'll see a two and a quarter foot opening by eight foot wide.
>> And
is that because
the outside diameter of the box is four by eight? And no, that doesn't make sense either because
jimmy: If
I don't know if the opening
to a four by eight foot box culvert is four by eight or if that's the outside diameter,
the inside might be
two by
>> six. I that's a clear opening. So,
it's clear opening
inside.
Okay.
>> So anyhow,
I think it's important that we have the drawing show
what we're really doing with respect to that culvert because I think that culvert is
important to making sure that we're
passing the flow that we expect to go there.
>> I think originally we started at four by eight. We realized that that was way too much more than we needed.
I got my plans right here. Let me grab.
>> If could,
I can add to that. So we originally talked about a
four by eight.
But like Andrew said,
we realized that
it was much, much bigger than what we needed.
And a three foot by eight
with
nine inches of
the date of soils placed on the inside
was sufficient to
to meet all the regulations that we were needing to meet in inflow and all that.
>> Okay.
But to be clear, and even when we went back and we talked at the last,
we were talking
about the minutes at the last last meeting we corrected them to say it's
four foot high by eight foot wide as opposed to eight foot high by four foot wide. So right now is the first we've ever mentioned
this being a three by eight culvert
as opposed to a four by eight culvert.
>> I think you're correct about that, Commissioner Larson.
And
I think what we need
here is the assurance that the
calculations
that
we've just addressed
regarding
upstream and downstream
impacts
are indeed
predicated
on the
actual size open diocese, a
three foot high by eight foot wide culvert
with a three quarter
foot
fill
at the base.
>> Yes, because the documentation submitted doesn't say anything about the size of the culvert.
>> From what I understand,
and maybe Carl can
add to this,
that the calculations were done at
the two foot 10
by
eight foot.
In other words, what's on the drawings?
>> Could
I just add something in here?
The
revised report
issued to Brandon
on
April
shows the
calculation.
The calculations were done for a three foot high
by eight foot wide concrete box culvert
in a 36 inches diameter HDP pipe.
And I said note that each culvert
will be filled to a nine inch depth
inside of space with normal stream materials.
And the result of that analysis
left us at the one hundred year storm level,
2.3 feet
below the top of the driveway.
So that was a three foot high by eight foot wide, that's in the report,
three foot wide
by three foot high concrete box culvert filled to nine inches.
The 36 inches pipe filled to nine inches.
And the analysis from that
gives us
a
level that is 2.3 feet below the top of the driveway
>> in the event of the 100 feet. I missed that when I looked through it then.
In my final question then is for
Eric. The last meeting you kind of briefed us on the overall
your project
and you had mentioned the fact that the
driveway
cost
was three times what your original estimate
for that was going to be.
Jimmy: And I was curious
as to what was the specific cost
to add to upgrade from the 36 inches plate to the box culvert.
>> George, can you do you remember that? Mean, you kind of priced that out.
Yes, so the box culvert
just to purchase them
is about $10,000
Each section weighs
approximately
11,000
pounds.
So it's gonna take a
very large piece of equipment in order to
maneuver them and place them.
So
with the cost of
the structure and the cost of mobilizing a piece of equipment like that,
that's where
all this additional cost is coming from.
I think there's, you know, transportation costs as well, right? The culvert section Yeah. Is gonna be
so George,
that final number, like somewhere between 15 to $20,000
Yeah, I think it was like somewhere
around 17 or $18,000
installed.
Okay.
That,
that takes care of my questions.
>> Okay.
And
you've already addressed the questions that I had, so I don't have any further questions either.
And I think we're now at a point where we can consider
action
on this application.
Entertain
a motion
to approve
the application
with conditions
to be specified
in discussion.
I believe
Agent Wagner has drawn up some.
I don't know if we have a summary motion at hand.
I would like a motion to
approve the application so that we can proceed.
I'll make a motion to approve the application.
Okay.
I'll move. I
>> will second. I would like it to refer to the specific
plans,
just as a
>> Okay, so we have a motion and a second to approve the application. Now we are open for discussion.
That would, of course, include the conditions
of approval.
Jim, you were saying
something about referring to plans. I don't I didn't quite understand that
comment.
>> One
condition that comes to mind is
we were it was represented that some mitigation we've done in terms of removal of some invasive species and replanting.
If we could perhaps
include that
in reference
the document
where that was proposed, and I believe it would have been
George,
the environmental consultant, that is working
on behalf of the applicant.
George Logan, I believe that was his second report.
Thank you.
>> Okay.
And
so
mitigation being one condition of approval,
maintenance being another condition of approval, as previously mentioned.
Agent Wagner, I believe that sometime
back, we did correspond a bit about
conditions of approval.
Did you have any further
recommendations
in that regard?
>> I
think I wrote
a draft of the mitigation
condition.
I sent it to you. I'm trying to find it now. I remember you I think you edited it a little bit. A few changes, but I'm backing off of those. I think we can basically reference
>> the environmental consultant's
report in terms of,
you know, what needs to be removed, namely barberry,
and what needs to be
planted,
namely
native
shrubs, native and adapted shrubs.
Yeah. Which were enumerated in the release.
>> Letter from George Logan to the chairman
was let's see.
There was there was a February 26, which I think is the one with the mitigation plan.
And then January 22 was the first one.
So you can make a motion to include
mitigation plan as submitted by
ecologist George Logan in his report on 02/26/2021.
And then the
most current
plan, I believe, is 03/10/2021,
The revision.
That would be what was what Jim was asking for.
>> I do have one comment.
Ideally,
the Commission has some control over
the timing of that mediation.
I'm not sure we
can in this situation.
I mean,
as I recall, some of the work would be done
possibly this year, and then there was a time period. I
don't know. I mean, I don't know as though we can tie it to
a CO or
I don't I don't think we can personally, but I just
I don't if if there's any way we could just
give our enforcement agent
some teeth here,
it'd be great.
But if not,
I can live with it.
>> I think that we have,
you know, two factors to consider. First of all,
vegetation removal, getting the barberry out
will depend on-site conditions.
Right now would be a really good time to do it,
but, you know, they're not on the site and they're not doing the work. But it should be certainly as early the removal should certainly be as early as possible in the
construction sequence. And I think our
agent
should be able to observe
that activity
when reviewing
the construction
as it proceeds.
The
secondary removal,
which will occur
the following season,
and then the subsequent planting
of
native and adapted vegetation
will be,
by that reckoning, about three years down the road.
So
I think it would be
an
action item
for
the agent.
But again, it's hard to put
a real timetable on it. And certainly,
in terms of the
final
approval,
I'm not sure that we're in a position to do that.
>> Okay. I I do appreciate that. I mean, there's a lot of factors here beyond the applicant's control. I mean, there's a lot of steps that
have to be mapped out,
things like financing and stuff.
>> Right.
For it to be done, it will be done quickly.
But
again, as you say, there's so much dependent on site conditions.
The mitigation is so much dependent on site conditions that it would be hard for us to specify
exactly when to do it.
Or again, we can,
you know, our agent is certainly cognizant
and will be cognizant of that.
And I think we can expect him to
be aware of those activities and look for those activities.
>> And perhaps for the record, we could
include something to the effect that,
remediation is
you know, by the time a CO is issued for the first dwelling, that remediation
would have been commenced and a plan for its completion, something like that, something that I think that the applicant could live with.
>> I think that's a fair
way of way of approaching it.
Agent Wagner, do you have any comments from an from an enforcement perspective here?
>> No. That makes sense to me because, just start it before
the final,
CO.
That's I don't know if it makes sense to me.
You can't really dictate when it's gonna end because
can't really be specific about that.
>> Right.
But certainly, you'll be out there during the first season
of construction.
You know,
obviously the,
I
don't know where the construction of that driveway would occur in the sequence of events, but I would expect it would be fairly early on.
And
again, if you've got equipment down there, that's going to be the time
to,
a good time to
go after
invasive removal.
Jed, did you have any comments
on
conditions of approval?
Nope.
>> Okay, so conditions of approval. Of course, standard conditions, but now we're including
the mitigation,
vegetation
removal and replacement,
and
the maintenance
as a condition,
are there
any further conditions that we should consider
as
relevant to this application.
>> Chairman Elliot,
enlighten me. Would we be imposing the standard conditions of things like
that, you know, the applicant notified the wetlands agent twenty four hours prior to construction, that sort of thing. Right. The the silt fence shall stay in place until
well, I mean, that that kind of information may be part of the ENS plan. I'm not positive. But nonetheless,
don't know if there's anything else just that we can give give our agent
to
work with.
Maybe it's all there.
I don't know.
It's
been a while.
>> Yeah,
it has.
I also think that for the record,
we should
make the finding
that
the
application
satisfies the criteria
and that there is no
reasonable and prudent alternative
to this activity.
Good point.
>> Okay.
We don't have,
I don't see Mindy on the call here.
Mindy's not here.
>> Mindy's gone. He's gone. Okay. Yeah, you must have been. Okay, we've got a, well, the meeting is being recorded.
I'm just concerned that we have,
you know, an accurate record of the conditions. I'm not in a position here to
draft a detailed motion on the fly,
but I want to make sure that we're clear
on
the, again, the grounds for
the
motion to approve the
application,
and that you know, that
the supplemental conditions
are clear,
I think that they will be,
how shall I say, they'll be reflected in the minutes of this meeting,
which we will consider at our next regular meeting.
And I hope that that will be adequate
as far as commissioners and applicants
are concerned
so that we can again proceed
to act on the application.
>> K. Can I go back to to brand
Brandon's
letter? Can we can we at least get certifications
that may not be worded?
It could be worded just
to the effect that, you know, to the best of the
well,
could could they be worded
to satisfy
both engineer or at least something that that Andrew
is comfortable with and provides some level of certification?
>> Well, we do have a record
in,
at
this meeting,
a statement. Do you want something in writing to
back up
the
assertion that's already made
>> to the effect. I can't tell you exactly what it would say, but it would be
I mean, obviously, Andrew made it clear that he he can't
he can't
comply
to to Brandon's request
to the full extent, but perhaps we could have something
something in the record.
Alright. It's not a deal breaker for me. I it was just a thought.
>> This
is agent Wagner here. I just feel like
the signature on the report with the professional
engineer stamp kinda
counts
Okay. Counts towards
a mistake in the professional reputation on
On the conclusions that he makes in the report,
so.
What
else you really need?
>> Should we summarize the motion? Is that what you're looking for, Chairman Elliott?
>> Yeah,
I want to make sure that we have a clear sense of the motion.
Since I don't have anything drafted in writing,
we are,
first of all, finding that
the activity is permissible and there's no
reasonable,
prudent
alternative
to the proposed
activity, to the construction of this
crossing,
that we will
include as,
in addition to the standard conditions of approval,
such as notification
and so forth,
that
applicants undertake
removal
of
barberry
specifically,
and that they plant
native and adapted
shrubs as
delineated
in the environmental consultant's
report,
and that they undertake
to maintain
the span
to avoid blockage
and,
you know, backup
in the event of a flood or of a
1%
rainfall event.
I believe that that was
all
the conditions that we were going to
require
to issue a permit.
>> For clarity, I just I'd like
the the approval to to reference the the plan that was submitted, the
a
title, a date, and a revision revised through.
Just so
for clarity,
I realized this plan is not necessarily filed in the land records, but nonetheless,
>> it's somewhere on record. It's in our archives. You know? Right. The town's archives. And that that was the again, h one, I believe that was the March 10 plan. Or Yeah, it's a last revision was March 10.
>> That will also be on the permit too.
That's part of the standard conditions
that the
permit
references
>> to plan last provision March So it's probably not required. Right? Probably not necessarily. I understand wetlands
nuances of wetlands. Always alluded to.
Thank
you.
>> Okay. Is there any further
discussion
regarding the motion?
Seeing none, then I'm going to ask for a vote.
Commissioner Halsey?
Aye.
Commissioner Larson?
And I, Vice Chairman Elliott, also vote aye. The motion carries three-zero-zero.
We approve the permit with, of course, conditions as described.
There'll be the two week waiting period,
and
Agent Wagner can take it from here.
Okay,
glad to have that off the agenda now.
We can move on to
agenda item number seven, enforcement actions.
First of all, we have a
show cause hearing
regarding
the
activities of the gravel pit on 497
Route 6.
Major Wagner, could you bring us up to date on that?
>> Yeah. I I
issued a
cease and desist and an order to remediate
yesterday,
May
for violation of the permit at
the
Route 6
gravel pit.
There
were some placement of stump
conditions on the
cease and desist letter is placement of stumps, tree limbs, and other woody debris within the 200 foot upland review area of the Hop River and within
the 100 foot upland review area of wetlands and vernal pools.
Stumps, tree limbs, and other woody debris have been placed in an area to the northeast of a line indicated on the site plan
revisions
six three twenty nineteen as the limit of grading, no grading beyond this point.
So basically no grading or removal or placement of fill, which includes stumps, tree limbs and other debris was to have occurred in that area.
And obviously I took some pictures, I emailed them to you because I didn't have
an assistant to post them on the website.
So you should have gotten those. You can see clear pictures of the stumps.
They're in the process of removing them, which is good.
And I think engineer
Chris Bell is on the call, and
he can give us an update of what's going on over there and answer any questions you guys have.
Okay.
>> Can
everybody hear me? Yep. Okay. My name is Chris Bell. I'm a professional engineer from Higinham representing the applicant.
I've been after the applicant for the last month to get rid of these stumps,
and we finally got started
Friday, last Friday.
As of today, we visited the site at 10:00.
Mr. Wagner,
Mr. Hallisey,
and Hank Bruner,
the
pathologist.
And
at the time we got out there, they had
two more loads to get rid of.
One load left
around 11:30.
And there was one more load to actually less than a load to be loaded on
after I left about
12:00.
The operator of the
the excavator loading the
stumps and debris.
I asked him to give me a call if he had any problems finishing that today. He hadn't called me.
I'm assuming they had no problem removing
the last load.
It takes about an hour round trip to come back
to bring the truck back. I'm
assuming they didn't have any problem with that. What was left,
if I could show the
Chairman
permission to share a plan.
>> Go right ahead.
That work? Uh-oh.
No. I'm not the host for this meeting. Okay. There we go. You got it? Yep. Okay. Good.
>> This
is the original
site plan that was approved.
Site plan s one. What I have shown in revision blocks are the changes
planned for the restoration plan as of this date. This was submitted
last week, I believe.
Where we are right now, this was the area
where the stumps
debris
was as of last week. They were actually located
along here
last month. These were at least pulled back away from
the wetland flags and the vernal pool last week, so it would be away from the buffer area.
These stumps were all removed
last week. This was the remainder spot
right here
that the rest of the stumps are,
I said, less than a load right here as of noon today.
What's left right in this area
between
Station
5 Plus 35 and 565
right here
is remainder of the soil
that's left from the stumps
because they were sitting there for a little while and they got dried out when the
stumps are lifted up, all the topsoil just falls off of them. There is
about a
three or four, maybe up to five foot layer
of a pile of top saw right here that will be taken care of. If
not, wasn't taken care of today, it will be taken care of should be tomorrow.
And in this area is going to be the first area that's going to get
restored as far as grading goes. All this material
that's here right now from the stumps is going to get taken out.
And since it's all topsoil,
it's
going to get put over here getting ready to get spread for the restoration area.
So as far as I know, all the stumps have been taken out and removed
off the site. They were trucked off the site as of today.
I believe
that
that was done. I can't say 100% it was, but all indications were that most likely did get finished. I will check on that 09:00 tomorrow morning to make sure that
got done.
The other thing that had to get done today, talked with Hank Brunner. This area right here of silt fence
is the
stakes are broken and
they're going to be putting
in a new fence in back of this and stabilizing that.
They should have done that this afternoon.
I will check to see if it's on tomorrow morning to make sure that's done.
Uh-uh mister Gruner said it's imperative that we get that done as soon as possible because this is the egg laying season now for the box turtles and we want to make sure they do not penetrate
any of these areas of silt fence.
All the silt fence along here has been inspected
and it's been maintained
throughout the project. We
look after every
rainstorm to make sure that it's intact. We'll be monitoring it
on Tuesday
when we come back
and make sure everything is okay through here.
We did start the grading over in this area this afternoon
with the bulldozer to start developing the slope
to bring the
slope down in the first restoration area here. This entire area here is going to be restored.
Half this pile is already gone since last week. It was stopped during
right after the cease and desist was issued
by
planning and zoning. And now we've
established with the town engineer that was out there also for the meeting today that we're going to be restoring from here
all the way back
to the end. It's going to be totally restored.
All the gravel that's along here along the silt fence will be removed
up to Station 4
I'm sorry, up to Station 380,
which is right here.
And this entire area will be restored all the way back to here. That way, the only
section that's actually open
is going to be right along
this border
where they'll start again if the Planning and Zoning Commission grants us the extension.
We'll
be
taking this pile out and then starting removal
here.
And we will be
make sure we stay on top of them to restore
this section as we go. Once this gets completed,
we'll be restoring that section.
The last thing we should probably note
when this is restored, and we're going to put a silt fence along the top soil that's there,
because this naturally flows in this direction.
We'll be installing a small sediment pond here
so that it collects the drainage water before it overflows
into
the sideline area over here.
We will have a swale
reconstructed
here to go towards the
sediment base, and it it got filled in over time over the last year,
and really isn't there anymore. So that's gonna be reestablished.
But that's the update on the plan right now. And, it is
hope that,
by the end of next week, this will be entirely
graded.
And
by,
Tuesday, this should be Tuesday, Wednesday, this area should be graded for Mr. Runner to come back
and
just note that there's sufficient amount of sand area
for the turtle laying area.
He no longer wants to have moguls. He thinks that this area is a flat area, would be better
served to be for
the egg laying area. So that's what we're going to give him. He'll take a look at that as soon as that's done.
And we hopefully by the end of next week,
we'll be ready to topsoil and see
the entire
restoration area.
All this topsoil that's located up here will come down and get spread across here,
and
most of the topsoil here is going to get spread
in the restoration area.
This topsoil has not been removed, so that will be used for
its own restoration.
And that's really about the update as of today.
Any questions from the commissioners?
>> Chairman Elliott, I
am interested in understanding
the what
are the actions
going forward
for the Wetlands Commission with regard to this application
extension.
Once
the plan that's just been described sounds good,
the current
application
expires the end of June, I think.
And when planning and zoning meets on this on the eighteenth,
do we need to have something from the Wetlands
Agency
to allow us to act on that application at that time?
>> That's a good question. I'm sorry that I can't answer it off the top of my head. I will have to refer to regulations
and
see if we need to take any action
on what what we have on the agenda tonight. So agent Wagner?
>> Yeah. I just
this is agent Wagner. I
looked at the I tried to go back and look at the the motion
for the original issuance of the permit,
and
they said
I forget who did it, but it was
a motion to approve it with standard
conditions, and then there were some other conditions. But the standard condition on the permit
and the regulations is five years.
And that was before
those previous wetlands agent didn't write permits,
so there's really nothing to research.
So I'd say if you go by standard permit conditions being five years,
they still got a few more years.
Being said,
if
the applicant is restoring
the area that's in the upland review area,
it really shouldn't
fall under the purview of the Wetlands Commission unless they choose to. They have the opportunity to review any application that might have an effect on an upland review area, even if it's out or or on a wetland, even if it's outside of
the 100 foot or the 200 foot, depending on where it is.
But yeah. So it may not even it may be a a moot point for the wetlands commission
if once the restoration is completed.
>> I mean, I think it's a matter of course that
zoning agent would probably ask the the wellizage if if the cease and desist if the applicant has
satisfactorily
addressed
the deficiencies.
Mhmm.
It's just
sort of operating per standard operating procedure.
>> And
so is that is that a question that the commission answers or the agent answers? Because we don't have another wetlands meeting scheduled before we have the next
planning and zoning meeting, which I said was the eighteenth, but it's actually the twenty first.
>> I believe the agent can
make the determination whether or not the the cease and desist could be lifted.
Like, act acting as the enforcement officer.
So if they
the responsibility to either issue or
conclude that that it's that it's been resolved.
So I should be able to take care of that before
before the next wetlands commission meeting. It sounds like it should be completed as long as everything goes to plan.
Okay,
thanks.
>> I certainly be satisfied with that outcome as well.
Okay, so
bottom line with this one,
action was taken and
the alpinins are the
engineer and the
construction company are
actively
responding.
And
our agent will
lift the
order
as soon as the response is completed.
Okay, I guess we can move on then to
the next enforcement action, the long standing
activity at 33 Route 87.
Thank you, John.
Thank you, Chris. Okay.
Thanks for being on the call, Chris.
Good night.
>> Agent Wagner, you had,
again, provide some photographs and
updates
on activities
at Number 33 Route 87.
Could you walk us through that?
>> Yeah.
Forget where I think the driveway was cut as of the last meeting.
Right.
So the shed got moved.
I believe it was 10 feet according to the plan.
So 10 feet away from the from the stream. And then
the contractor,
Mark Williams, came in and
removed some material behind the shed,
removed some of the extra piles that were over there, and then used
some large stone
to,
he basically laid it on the the slope behind the shed.
As you can see in the pictures, he pressed it in with the with the excavator bucket so that,
it wouldn't fall into the stream.
I emphasize when I talked to him to
maintain this, you know, not
try to remove material from the stream beds since it was already established and
there was no blockage. There was no you know, it's all vegetated,
so we didn't wanna go down there. So it's basically the the area leading up into the, you know, maybe
six feet up from the stream bed in certain spots.
Yeah. So I went and took a look at it today.
Mark Williams, the contractor,
completed everything.
I think all of these is some grass seed
in certain areas. A lot of it's rock,
but it looks
looks pretty satisfactory. The angle is much better than it was when the commission visited the site, and you could see the real steep angles that's that's been
resolved.
So then I also visited
with the owner of 41 Route 87
earlier today too. And
because she voiced some concerns with the activity over there, I think she was
thinking that
the owner of 31 Or 33 Route 87 was doing work without a permit. So I explained to her the the permit and and
the extent of work and assured her that they were done over there, and they weren't doing anything further. And now she seemed satisfied
with that.
So
so I think we're we're in a good place with this one.
I'm Good. I'm happy with the work that was done over there. Good. I'm glad to hear that it's finally approaching resolution.
>> I
don't remember the details
of the
engineering
design,
and I don't know if they fulfilled
all those
criteria in the application or,
for example, using geotextile.
>> That I did talk to
Mark about,
and we kinda came to the conclusion that that wouldn't work in the application because of the rocks.
I was thinking that the weight of the rocks would tear the geotextile, and he agreed
that if you put the, you know, you put the fabric down so you'd have to remove all the rocks, put the fabric down, put the rocks back down, and then press them into place, you'd probably tear the material Okay.
Accomplish anything.
I mean, if it was being seeded
and topsoil is being placed on it, then you'd kinda need it to stabilize the area. But being that
that the steeper grades are all rock and filled, so
It was really kinda unnecessary.
>> Okay.
There we go.
Any other questions,
comments from the commissioners?
I just see it wrapped up.
>> Good to have it getting done.
Okay,
then we can move on, I guess, to agenda item number eight, agent report.
We've
got
three or four items there. You want to walk us through it briefly?
>> Okay. I got
the first one is the 85 Lakeside Drive. I don't have any updates on that one. It's still working its way through zoning. So
I'll
let you know when that gets issued.
I issued a permit for
agent approval of
the town of Andover's application to install a 12 by four foot wooden stairway
at
it's in the Upland Review area, the Hop River. It's actually behind the the ball fields. There's a walking trail over there. Guess you guys are probably much more familiar with it than I am.
But I went out and visited the site with Scott Person and
explained to me as a 12 by four 12
feet long, four feet wide.
It's gonna be set in between two
rocks and kinda work its way down. It's already kinda like, there's no excavating
or anything. They're gonna set the post as far as they can,
dig the holes without running into rocks.
So I thought that was a pretty straightforward
application.
And then the next one,
I had a report of some activity
at 159
Lakeside Drive.
I didn't see a wetlands permit on file.
There were two building permits
that were issued,
for a propane tank and a generator installation.
They were
filled out in October
2020.
So I spoke with the owner
May 17,
and
he was a little
he was not aware that he needed a wetlands permit. He had talked to the the previous
building admin person, I think. I'm not sure.
I didn't remember seeing the
building permits because I usually review them when they come in here to see if they do need a permit.
So basically, what he was doing over there was
they placed
a propane tank, they placed a generator, and then they needed to dig a trench to bury the gas lines and the electric lines out to the pole, hook it up, and then the gas line to connect the generator and the propane tank.
And I believe that's been completed now.
And then there's another one
for
a pending approval of replacement
of a septic system at 84 Route 6, which is Scott Electrocraft.
So they're they're putting a septic system within a 100
Upland review area of unnamed tributary of the Hop River.
Is
Evan Harvinson on the call?
I am.
>> Okay. Yeah. He's the the
applicant, so he could explain the project to you guys if you want.
You can go ahead, Evan.
>> The existing system for Scott Electrocrash is underneath their parking lot.
Every year in the spring,
their system backs up, so it's being affected by groundwater.
When it was originally installed, it's, like, 40 something years old.
So this year, they reached out to us. It's the first year we've actually serviced them specifically,
asked us to look into the issue. That's what we kinda came up with was that the existing system is being affected by groundwater.
They had previously done soil testing on the property.
I believe it was o eight
in anticipation
to put a addition on their building.
So the testing was done.
They found 100% code compliant area.
Plans were approved at that time in 2008
for the building addition based on the soil testing that was done for the 100% co opine area. That co opine area just so happens to be
within the 100 foot of
an active stream,
but it's only a portion of the septic.
The overall length of the system is about 140
feet long.
There's one
thirty foot leg that's gonna be within that 100 foot range. It'll actually be at sixty sixty feet
from the edge of the creek.
The rest of it is outside of the 100 foot range.
Joe and I met on-site and kind of walking through that exact thing.
He took some pictures.
My opinion, the creek is easily
protectable with just silt fence
during construction. And then after construction,
due to the slope on the hill, we're probably going to end up putting down
hay matting, something like that to stabilize the slope,
at least temporarily until vegetation and things can grow in there
before we would pull the sill fence. That's kind of
the quick, rough
explanation.
I can take whatever questions you guys got.
Anything from the Commissioners?
>> Yeah, I have a question of of the applicant, if I may, to the commit to the chair.
Sure. I'm just trying to understand the plan
towards the top of the page near the screen.
What am I looking at? There's there's a silk fence identified,
and then there's this
40 foot strip.
Can you tell me what Joe that
>> wanted to know the distance from creek to silk fence. So that is that measure. So
there's 40 feet of separation between the edge of the creek and the silt fence that we're going to put in.
>> That's the strip that you're seeing. And what would the 60 feet be?
>> That is the distance from the edge of the creek to the actual edge of the septic system. So where it says
32 feet of double wide.
That
is the edge of the system. So the measurement from edge of creek to edge of system is 60 feet.
>> Okay.
Just just a sort of general question. I
mean, this is obviously very close to the stream.
I have to
I can't picture the lot. I mean, I I mean, I drive by it all the time and it
I mean, it must have been placed
here, you know, closed here because this is where it fits.
Right? I mean, there weren't a lot of options. Correct?
>> Yeah. So there's it's twofold one because this is where it fits into because
everywhere else they tested was unsuitable,
which means there's less than 18 inches of naturally occurring
suitable soils.
So I I can't shift it, you know, further away from the creek
Okay. Because you get into unsuitable soils, and then I can't go in their parking lot
as is the existing system because of the groundwater. It'd be in the groundwater.
Okay. Thank you. So this is elevated up on a slope, up on a if you went by there now, there's a bunch of trees up on that slope. So
Thank you.
Any other questions or comments?
>> I
did not have a question on this one, but I did have a question on the previous one
when you get We'll to
>> get back to that. Let's make sure we,
again, this is simply
a report. I don't think any action is required on our part.
And
no need to
keep
the applicant on the call any longer necessary.
So, if we're done with discussion on that,
we can again return to the question you had
regarding the other item on the report.
>> Is for Adrian on
the 159
Lakeside Drive.
As I walked by there, I see it
looks like there's
pallets of maybe building stone or something like that in the vicinity where that trench was.
And you said you looked through the different building permits.
Did you know, was there any evidence like he's building a patio or anything like that with that stuff? Or did you get a feel for what that was all about?
>> No, all I was told was
that there was propane tank and the generator installed. I haven't seen
any permits or anything for for patios or
or anything like that. I
>> recall saying a zoning permit for the
the the
generator
or the or the tank. What what did you say?
Was it both? Propane
>> tank and a generator. There are two separate permits for one for each.
>> Okay. I do remember signing off on that. I
can't speak.
I have no idea how it moved forward without the wetland sign off.
And that's the standard procedure is the wetlands agent signs off,
whether it be, you know, after a permit is issued or,
you know, the administrative
approval is given.
>> Yeah. I
looked through the guy the applicant's folder. I mean, it has a record of applying for permits
for everything that he does there, so
I don't think it was an intentional thing. I think it was just overlooked.
>> Yeah. He he came before the commission last year for a septic system.
Right.
I worked with him on that.
>> Okay. I have one
more comment.
And as I was looking through
Scott Persson's application, and he had
the entering boilerplate couple of pages before you get to the actual application
thing. And
it talked about Andover Lake activities.
In a couple of meetings ago, we were having a discussion about should the commission
act on
applications
within 200 feet of the lake?
And at that time I said to you I was happy with the way things were going.
But when I was reading through Scott Persson's
application that actually had this
cover page on there,
it specifies under Andover Lake activities that the Commission regulates all activities
within 200 feet of Andover Lake, including any activity within the lake itself.
So I guess based on that,
maybe that was the basis of Megan's comment
that the Commission should be
involved in any application within 200 feet of the lake.
And I guess I agree with it.
>> I
disagree somewhat with that interpretation.
My understanding was it was simply a matter
not necessarily that we should have to act on every application,
but rather that
a higher level of scrutiny might be warranted
simply because of, again, the density
of population in the lake and
the particular sensitivity.
However,
I think we can still rely on agent approval
for upland review,
and especially since we're getting
better communication
about those actions,
that
I don't think we need to
put our foot in
any further
on
you know, Lake Upland review applications. Obviously, when we get down to the
things that are on the lake margin, things like retaining walls,
yeah, we should be out there taking a look at those.
But I don't see that we need to do that for,
no,
for activities like propane tank and generator.
Now, that said,
I would certainly like to see an application
for that activity.
I
don't think that it's proper
to
let that kind of activity slide,
even if it was simply
inadvertent
and
other
permits were issued
for the activity.
It's
awkward to be
approving an application
after
the work is done, but I think it's even more awkward
to
let an activity slide without
requiring an application.
>> So in the case of Mr. Carbonos
coming before the commission
to put in a septic tank,
septic system last year,
we would
now view that as something that agent Wagner could approve?
>> I think so, since, especially since septic systems are subject
to,
you know,
health district regulations and all that.
And I think that, again, the Commission
has been on record of heartily approving septic system upgrades
in the Andover Lake area
because of the
history
of,
you know,
under engineered and failing septic systems,
impacting
the lake quality.
>> Okay. Just wanted to make sure my expectations were clear. I
>> do want to remind the Commission too that they have
the ability to appeal anything,
any decisions that I make. If I do something that you don't agree with,
you could definitely bring it up and then review it through the commission.
Right.
But that's why I try to give keep you updated so that hopefully you can decide if you wanna take it on before before I approve it. So
>> And I think you're doing a good job on that too. So I
think it I think it is working.
>> The other other thing, Jed, was sometimes
when I post the applications,
I
most of the ones I put on there, I think I take the two and overlay the cover pages
off of the form, you know, just to limit what's on the web because they're preprinted.
There's no information on them. So
I just wanna make sure it's it's not the applicant that's omitting that stuff. It's it's usually me. I can include it if you if you'd like. But
>> Nope. That's fine. Okay. I just actually took the time to read through it today.
Yeah,
>> I would like to see more
update on, for example, the Long Hill
Road
logging and stump removal
application. I believe you approved that.
And, you know, there were questions
raised about that application
at the last meeting.
And,
you know, I appreciate,
you know, returning
to when you
end up
approving an application, that we've considered
if you would give us a debriefing
on that as well, and, you know, especially where there were issues like property lines and
so forth that that
were of concern to the commissioners. So if you'd
be sure to include those in your agent report,
I would certainly appreciate it.
>> Yeah. Did with Long Hill Road when I didn't get an updated
map showing the correct property line that went down to the stream. So the guy
did did
cut his own trees down.
Good.
>> Good. And as for removing the stumps, last time I
drove by there,
I didn't see anything further. I it didn't sound like talking to him that he was gonna do it right away. So Okay.
Well So is
>> it your intent to have him submit an application when he does the stump removal? Or The
>> application,
the one that he had was
it did include stump removal in it. Okay.
He had talked about putting a shed there in the future. I told him he would need a
different application for that. So
but I think the the one I approved was stumps
and
trees.
The whole tree, I guess.
Okay.
>> Good.
Well, let's see now. I guess we can move on to the agenda.
Other business?
I don't think we have any.
I have a You do have?
>> Question.
Just
on the it's my understanding there were some
applicants for
slots.
>> Oh, that's the next item on the agenda, appointment of new Oh, okay. Didn't I didn't have the agenda in front of me. Right. I understand. I'm sorry.
There it is.
>> Joe, you've had
some correspondence
with a couple of people that were
interested or expressed interest in the commission.
I
believe
one was actually on the call earlier,
but if you could give us an update on that.
>> Yeah. I actually
I was glad she was here because I meant to send her and Tim the agenda. I did it for the last one that got canceled, but then I slipped my mind this time because it came up so quick.
Yeah.
But I was hoping to have Tim
here too.
Michelle was kind of
wavering about it. She was wondering if her experience was
was adequate.
But I told her, you know, the difference in experience is is good, I was hoping she could be here to to
talk about what she could bring to the commission in front of you guys. But
I guess she's not here. So maybe the next meeting, I'll I'll send her a keep her in the loop.
>> Yeah. Why don't you send out invitations for the next meeting? We'll put her earlier on the agenda.
Yeah,
yeah, hopefully.
>> Maybe it'll be a light agenda. We'll be able to talk to them, because obviously,
I mean, here we have a quorum of three.
Mr. Hallison is not going to continue the commission,
so we're down to
three regular members with one alternate,
and we
really need to
flush out the board a little bit. So, invite
them in.
I guess I now have their contact information
because you've copied
me
on your correspondence,
so I should contact them as well to invite them to apply
for
membership.
We can take it from there.
And of course, we can always hope that continued
publicity
will drum up further interest.
That said, I don't think there's anything more we can do right now.
So, we'll move on to our
next item, which is our next regular meeting,
which will be on
07/13/2021.
Of course,
meeting because of the Independence Day holiday.
I look forward to seeing at least Mr. Larson and perhaps some of our other commissioners as well.
Again, I'll take this opportunity to express appreciation
to
Jim Halsey for
serving on the Commission, and I'm
sorry that your
responsibilities
and
voting agent put
you in a conflicted situation.
I certainly understand that.
It was my pleasure to serve. Good.
>> So,
with that,
we can, I think, move to our final item on the agenda, which would be a move motion to adjourn?
I'll move to adjourn. I'll second.
All in favor?
>> Aye. Aye. Okay.
So, the meeting is adjourned
at 08:34PM.
Again, thanks to all in attendance,
and see you
on the thirteenth.
With that, we can all
push the little red button that says leave the meeting.
Good night.
Enjoy the rest of it.
Good night. Good night, everybody.
Live long and prosper.